这对我们来说应该是非常熟悉的：标记为A且单个的坐标系
This should be very familiar to us by now: a coordinate frame labeled A and a single
点。我们可以通过关于帧A的向量来描述该点
point. We can describe the point by a vector with respect to frame A. The leading A in
P的前面表示。我可以用它的组件来编写这个向量-它
front of the P indicates that. I can write this vector in terms of its components - its
沿XA轴和YA轴的距离以及单位矢量XA和YA帽。现在，我们来吧
distances along the XA axis and the YA axis and the unit vectors XA and YA hat. Now, let’s
引入一个新的坐标系，框架B，它具有相同的旋转原点
introduce a new coordinate frame, frame B, and it has got the same origin that’s rotated
以角度Theta。我可以通过关于坐标系的向量来描述该点
by the angle Theta. I can describe the point by a vector with respect to coordinate frame
B和我可以用单位矢量XB和YBhat来表示它们并且它们被指示
B and I can write that in terms of the unit vectors XB and YB hat and they’re indicated
这里是红色的。我可以用cosTheta和正弦Theta来编写XBhat的表达式，
here in red. I can write expressions for XB hat in terms of cos Theta and sine Theta,
我可以用正弦Theta和cosTheta来为YB帽子写一个表达式。如果
and I can write an expression for YB hat in terms of minus sine Theta and cos Theta. If
我将这两个方程代入这里，我可以写出这个表达式。然后我可以扩展，
I substitute these two equations into here, I can write this expression. Then I can expand,
重新排列和分解XA帽子和YA帽子。接下来要注意的是因为这些
rearrange and factor out XA hat and YA hat. The next thing to observe is because these
两个坐标系共享一个原点，然后矢量AP和BP实际上完全相同
two coordinate frames share an origin, then the vector AP and BP are in fact exactly the
相同。XAhat的系数必须相同，所以我们可以写出来。而且，系数
same. The coefficients of XA hat must be the same, so we can write this. And, the coefficients
YA帽子必须是相同的，所以我们可以写这个。我们来看看这两个表达式。
of YA hat must be the same, so we can write this. Let’s take those two expressions.
稍微简化一下，我们现在可以用矩阵形式写出来。如果你有点儿
Simplify things a little bit and we can now write this in matrix form. If you’re a little
不确定这个步骤，然后只是将它加倍，你会发现你得到了
unsure about this step, then just multiply it out and you’ll find that you get the
上面的表达。现在，我们更简洁地编写矢量部分。而不是在
expressions above. Now, we write the vector part more concisely. Instead of in terms of
它的各个元素，我们将其写为关于特定坐标的符号P.
its individual elements, we write it as the symbol P with respect to a particular coordinate
帧。因此，该表达式将关于帧B的向量与具有的向量相关联
frame. So, this expression relates the vector with respect to frame B to the vector with
通过将矢量B的分量乘以该2×2来实现
respect to frame A. It is achieved by multiplying the components of vector B by this 2 x 2
矩阵。我们可以使表达更简洁
matrix. We can make the expression even more concise
并写这样的。并且，我们引入符号R来表示旋转矩阵。
and write it like this. And, we introduce the symbol R to represent a rotation matrix.
这是一种非常简洁的方式来表示不同的两个向量之间的关系
This is a very concise way of representing the relationship between two vectors in different
坐标框架，它们通过旋转矩阵R相关。这里我们有相同的
coordinate frames, and they are related by a rotation matrix R. Here we have the same
像以前一样表达，并且要更精确一些，更加小心，我们会添加一些
expression as before, and to be a bit more precise, a bit more careful, we will add some
标签到矩阵R，我们将放置一个前导A和一个尾随B.并且，这表明
labels to the matrix R and we will put a leading A and a trailing B. And, this indicates that
R是一个旋转矩阵，它将矢量从B帧旋转到A帧。这很重要
R is a rotation matrix that rotates a vector from frame B to frame A. It’s important
要注意并且不要混淆：矩阵R取决于框架的旋转角度
to note and not be confused by this: the matrix R depends on the rotation angle from frame
A到框架B.这两件事的顺序是不同的，不会被绊倒
A to frame B. The order of these two things is different and don’t get tripped up by
那。我们来看看旋转矩阵。
that. Let’s have a look at the rotation matrix.
像这样的矩阵被称为正交矩阵或有时称为正交矩阵。
A matrix like this is referred to as an orthogonal matrix or sometimes an orthonormal matrix.
此矩阵中的每一列都是一个单位向量，您可以自己展示它
Each column in this matrix is a unit vector and you can show that for yourself pretty
容易。矩阵中的每列与其他列正交。在这种情况下，那里
easily. Each column in the matrix is orthogonal to the other columns. In this case, there
只有两列，你可以很容易地显示由第一列形成的向量
are only two columns and you can show, again very easily, that a vector formed by the first
列与第二列形成的矢量正交。点的产品
column is orthogonal to the vector formed by the second column. The dot product of the
两列将等于零。正交矩阵的一个非常有用的特性是
two columns will be equal to zero. A really useful property of an orthogonal matrix is
它的反转与它的转置相同。计算矩阵的逆是相反的
that its inverse is the same as its transpose. Computing the inverse of a matrix is rather
复杂，而计算它的转置真的很简单。所以，这太好了
complex, whereas computing its transpose is really very simple. So, it’s great that
我们有一个矩阵，其逆可以通过转置元素来非常简单地计算
we have a matrix whose inverse can be computed very simply by transposing the elements of
矩阵。旋转矩阵的另一个属性是
the matrix. Another property of the rotation matrix is
它的行列式总是等于1.这意味着，如果我乘以任何向量
that its determinant is always equal to 1. And this means that, if I multiply any vector
通过该矩阵，矢量的长度不变。那是一个重要的财产
by this matrix, the length of the vector is unchanged. That’s an important property
旋转矩阵当我将矢量从一个坐标框架旋转到另一个坐标框架时，它会
of a rotation matrix. When I rotate a vector from one coordinate frame to another, its
长度不变。数学家会说像这样的旋转矩阵属于
length is not changed. A mathematician would say that a rotation matrix like this belongs
到二维的特殊正交群。而且，象征性地，我们写下了这一点
to the special orthogonal group of dimension two. And, symbolically, we’d write that
因为R是一个元素-属于-集合SO（2），特殊的正交维度组
as R is an element of - belongs to - the set SO(2), special orthogonal group of dimension
这是上面的表达。并且，如果我将旋转矩阵穿过另一个
2. Here’s the expression from above. And, if I take the rotation matrix across the other
等号的一面，我可以写这个。这表明如果我想旋转一个
side of the equal sign, I can write this. This indicates that if I want to rotate a
从坐标框架A到坐标框架B的向量，我使用了旋转的倒数
vector from coordinate frame A into coordinate frame B, I use the inverse of the rotation
从坐标框架A到坐标框架B的矩阵。并且，请记住，它的倒数
matrix from coordinate frame A to coordinate frame B. And, remember, that the inverse of
旋转矩阵就是它的转置。第一个表达式中的标签A和B.
a rotation matrix is simply its transpose. The labels A and B in this first expression
是完全一般的，我完全适合交换A和B和
are completely general and it’s completely proper for me to swap the A and the B and
现在我可以写这个。这两个方程是等价的。所以，现在我可以写这个了
now I can write this. These two equations are equivalent. So, now I can write this and
这非常重要。它所说的是坐标系的旋转矩阵
this is really important. What it says is the rotation matrix from coordinate frame
B坐标框架A是坐标框架的旋转矩阵的倒数
B to coordinate frame A is the inverse of
A来协调框架B.让我们看一下MATLAB中的一些具体例子。
A to coordinate frame B. Let’s have a look at some concrete examples of this in MATLAB.
首先，我将使用Toolbox命令创建一个二维旋转矩阵
First of all, I’m going to create a two-dimensional rotation matrix using the Toolbox command
rot2用于二维旋转矩阵。而且，我要问一个旋转角度
rot2 for rotation matrix in two dimensions. And, I’m going to ask for a rotation angle
0弧度。并且，这是2x2旋转矩阵，它是单位矩阵。它的
of 0 radians. And, here is the 2 x 2 rotation matrix and it is the identity matrix. It’s
在对角线上得到1，在对角线上得到0。我可以要求相应的轮换
got 1s on the diagonal and 0s on the off diagonal. I can ask for a rotation that corresponds
到一个角度说naught点2弧度，这是旋转矩阵。我还可以
to an angle say of nought point 2 radians and this is that rotation matrix. I can also
以度为单位指定角度。因此，例如，我可以要求角度R为30度
specify the angle in degrees. So, for instance, I could ask for the angle R of 30 degrees
这是相应的旋转矩阵。我要做的就是把结果
and this is the corresponding rotation matrix. What I’m going to do is to put that result
在工作空间变量R中，这里再次旋转矩阵用于旋转
in to the workspace variable R and here is the rotation matrix again for a rotation of
正30度。现在，我们刚才谈到了这个具有数字的旋转矩阵
positive 30 degrees. Now, we talked a moment ago about this rotation matrix having a number
属性，其中一个属性是列是正交的。所以我
of properties, and one of the properties was that the columns are orthogonal. So, I’m
要创建一个代表矩阵第一列的变量，另一个变量
going to create a variable which represents the first column of a matrix, another variable
它对应于矩阵的第二列。而且，如果我看看点积
which corresponds to the second column of the matrix. And, if I look at the dot product
在这两个向量中，我们可以看到它等于0.我们提到的另一个属性
of those two vectors, we can see that it is equal to 0. Another property that we mentioned
是矩阵的行列式等于正1，我们可以很容易地验证
is that the determinant of the matrix is equal to positive 1 and we can quite easily verify
那。我们谈到的另一个属性是矩阵的逆是相同的
that. Another property we talked about is that the inverse of the matrix is the same
作为它的转置。因此，使用MATLAB内置函数计算矩阵的逆矩阵
as its transpose. So, the inverse of the matrix is computed using the MATLAB built in function
inv，并使用引用运算符计算转置，我们可以看到
inv, and the transpose is computed using the quote operator just like that and we can see
很明显，反转等于转置。
quite clearly that the inverse is equal to the transpose.
最后，我们可以将此旋转矩阵可视化为旋转坐标系。要做到这一点，
Finally, we can visualize this rotation matrix as a rotated coordinate frame. To do that,
我使用工具箱函数trplot2。它是二维变换图的缩写。
I use the Toolbox function, trplot2. It’s a short for transform plot in two dimensions.
我传入了我感兴趣的旋转矩阵，并且有一个坐标的表示
I pass in the rotation matrix that I’m interested in and there is a representation of the coordinate
帧。现在，它看起来有点奇怪，因为我需要将轴缩放设置为相等和
frame. Now, it looks a little bit odd because I need to set the axis scaling to equal and
在这里，我们看到一个直角坐标框架显示为蓝色，我们可以看到它
here we see a right angled coordinate frame shown here in blue and we can see that it
相对于世界坐标系旋转。
is rotated with respect to the world coordinate frame.